Finding Aid for Lawrence K. Rosinger Papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lawrence K. Rosinger Papers 1937-1994, 1937-1973
Rosinger, Lawrence K. (Lawrence Kaelter), 1915-
2 linear feet
9541 Aa 2
China expert, worked for Foreign Policy Association and American Institute of Pacific Relations, traveled extensively in China 1946 interviewing many leaders Communist and nationalist parties, traveled to China again in 1973, author of numerous books and articles on China, came under attack by the McCarran Committee's Senate investigation following Chinese revolution. Papers include correspondence, notes and drafts for writings, transcripts of radio broadcasts, transcripts and other material relating to the McCarran Committee investigation and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 8328 ) was received from Mrs. Lillian Rosinger in two accessions in 1995.
The collection is open for research.
Lawrence K. Rosinger was born in New York City on October 5, 1915. He received his B.A. in history from the City College of New York in 1932 and a master's degree in Far Eastern studies from Columbia University in 1936. From 1937 to 1941, Rosinger taught history and civilizations courses in New York high schools, and from 1941 to 1942, he worked as assistant to the India Government Trade Commissioner. Rosinger worked as a research associate with the Foreign Policy Association from 1941 to 1942. During this same period, he was awarded two visiting lectureships by Columbia and the University of California-Berkeley.
In 1946, Rosinger made his first trip to China. Traveling as a correspondent for the Foreign Policy Association and also representing several other American publications, he had an excellent opportunity to gather firsthand information. During his trip, he traveled some 5,000 miles by train, car, ship and even on horseback within China. He visited Shanghai, Peiping (Beijing), Yenan, the Yellow River area, and Manchuria. He interviewed more than two dozen Chinese Communist leaders and some third-party spokesmen, as well as high-ranking officials of the Nationalist Party. By the late 1940s, he had established himself as an expert in the field of Far Eastern studies. In 1948 he began to work as a research associate for the American Institute of Pacific Relations.
Throughout the 1940s and early 1950s, Rosinger was a highly respected expert in Far Eastern studies. He was consulted regularly by the U.S. State Department regarding China and Far Eastern policies. He was a prolific writer. Besides six books, four on China, and two on India, he also wrote more than one hundred articles, book reviews, and radio broadcasts. He was also a very active public speaker. While working for the American Foreign Policy Association and the American Institute for Pacific Relations, he gave numerous talks to organizations each year.
After the Chinese Communist Party took power in 1949, and especially after the outbreak of the Korean War in 1950, Rosinger came under attack from right-wing supporters of Senator Joseph McCarthy in Congress for his allegedly pro-Communist views. In testimony before the McCarran Committee, a subcommittee in charge of investigating pro-Communist activities, Rosinger defended his position as a scholar of Chinese studies and his work with the American Institute of Pacific Relations.
In 1952, to remove himself from further political persecution, Rosinger moved to Detroit, Michigan. He first worked as a hardware store manager in Detroit and then taught at Henry Ford Community College for over twenty years. In 1973, Rosinger made his second trip to China with his wife Lillian Rosinger and five other Americans. For twenty-five days, they traveled as tourists, visiting such places as Canton (Guangzhou), Shanghai, Hangzhou, Chengzhou, Sian, Yenan and Beijing. In Beijing, Rosinger interviewed Marshall Ye Jianying, head of China's armed forces and one of the six top leaders of the country.
Rosinger retired in the early 1980s and died in 1994. He was survived by his wife, Lillian Rosinger, his son and daughter.
Lawrence K. Rosinger's papers document his research interest in far eastern studies in the 1940s and early 1950s, his two trips to China (in 1946 and 1973), as well as his activities during the McCarthy era.
The Lawrence K. Rosinger papers are divided into ten series:
Biographical Information, 1939-1994 (1 folder)
General Correspondence, 1937-1973 (8 folders)
McCarran Hearings, 1949-1953 (10 folders)
Newspaper Clippings, 1944-1953 (3 folders)
Publications, 1936-1951 (17 folders)
Radio Broadcasts, 1941-1945 (1 folder)
Speech Announcements, 1944-1951 (1 folder)
First Trip to China, 1946 (11 folders)
Second Trip to China, 1973 (5 folders)
Miscellaneous, 1948-1976 (1 folder)
Form and Genre:
Photographs.
Subjects:
Rosinger, Lawrence K. (Lawrence Kaelter), 1915-; Chou, En-lai, 1898-1976.; Jao, Shu-shih, 1901-; Mao, Tse-tung, 1893-1976.; American Institute of Pacific Relations.; Chung-kuo kuo min tang.; Foreign Policy Association.; Chung-kuo kung ch'an tang.; United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary. Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and other Internal Security Laws.; East Asia--History--Study and teaching.; China--History--Civil War, 1945-1949.; China--Politics and government--1945-1949.
- Biographical Information 1939-1994, 1 folders
  The Biographical Information series contains personal information, including materials relating to Rosinger's educational background, work experience and honors received. Materials in this series are arranged chronologically.
  - 1939-1994 (Box 1)
- General Correspondence 1937-1973, 8 folders
  The General Correspondence series reflects Lawrence Rosinger's strong research interest in far eastern studies in general and China in particular. Most of this is professional correspondence with his colleagues, academic advisors, editors, and publishers. The correspondence is arranged chronologically. Some of the correspondence generated between 1950 and 1952 contains information on the McCarran Committee's attack on Rosinger and the American Institute of Pacific Relations.
  - 1937-1973, 8 folders (Box 1)
- McCarran Hearings 1949-1953, 10 folders
  The McCarran Hearings series contains materials relating to the attacks on Lawrence Rosinger and the American Institute of Pacific Relations during the McCarthy era as well as to Rosinger's defense. Materials in this series include correspondence, memoranda, statements, transcripts of proceedings, and testimony. All materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Memorandums and Statements, 1950-1953, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Testimony, 1950-1953, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Transcripts of Round Table Discussion of American Foreign Policy toward China, Department of State, 1949, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Transcripts of Proceedings, Problem of U.S. Policy toward China, 1950, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings 1944-1953, 3 folders
  The Newspaper Clippings series includes clippings from the New York Times and from journals and periodicals regarding far eastern political, economic and military development as well as United States foreign policy. Materials in this series are arranged in chronological order.
  - 1944-1953, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Publications 1936-1951, 17 folders
  The Publications series has been divided into two parts. The first part, the bulk of the materials in this series, contains articles or book reviews written by Rosinger between 1937 and 1951 on far eastern countries. Most of the articles appeared in the Foreign Policy Bulletin, Far Eastern Survey and Ameriasia. The second part of the series consists of book reviews written by others on Rosinger's books on China and India.
  - Articles and Book Reviews by Lawrence Rosinger
    - Ameriasia, 1937-1940 (Box 1)
    - Asia Affairs, 1945-1948 (Box 1)
    - Far Eastern Survey, 1942-1943, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Foreign Policy Bulletin, 1942-1951, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Pacific Affairs, 1936-1939 (Box 1)
    - New Republic, 1944-1946 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1938-1951 (Box 2)
  - Book Reviews by Others on Lawrence Rosinger
    - China's Crisis, 1945 (Box 2)
    - China's Wartime Politics, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Restless India, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Forming a New China, 1948 (Box 2)
    - India and the United States, 1950 (Box 2)
    - The State of Asia, 1951 (Box 2)
- Radio Broadcasts 1941-1945, 1 folders
  The Radio broadcasts series contains transcripts of dozens of broadcasts written by Lawrence Rosinger during World War II. Most of these broadcasts focus on the political, social, and military developments in the far east. These broadcasts are often short, but objective. The provided not only a keen insight into the contemporary events in the far eastern countries, but are also excellent sources for researchers and United States foreign policy makers.
  - 1941-1945 (Box 2)
- Speech Announcements 1944-1951, 1 folders
  The Speech announcements series consists mainly of announcements for talks, seminar speech presentations, and conference speeches given by Lawrence Rosinger at various occasions between 1940 and 1953. Most speeches dealt with far eastern studies.
  - 1944-1951 (Box 2)
- Trip to China 1946, 11 folders
  The first trip to China series contains nearly 300 black and white photographs taken in China, notes and transcripts of more than two dozen interviews conducted with the Chinese Communist leaders, third party spokesmen, and high-ranking Nationalist Party officials. In those notes, one can find important biographical information of some Chinese Communist leaders that Rosinger interviewed, statistics of the population in the " Liberated Area" (Chinese Communist-controlled area), and the Chinese Communist Party members.
  Most of Rosinger's interviews took place during his visit to Yenan (July 21-August 1); some occurred in Shanghai, Nanking (now Nanjing), Peiping (now Peijing) and Tsaochow (now Chaochou). Among those interviews, the two lengthy interviews with Mao Tse-tung and with Chou En-lai are probably the most valuable. Also of interest is Rosinger's interview with Jao Sou-Shih, a high-ranking Chinese Communist Party official who was later purged by Mao Tse-tung. The subject matter of these interviews primarily focuses on political, economic and military developments in the period of the Nationalist-Communist coalition.
  Another interesting document in this series is a letter dated May 6, 1946, from Dr. L. Peng a professor at the Academia Sinica. In this long letter (34 pages), Dr. Peng discusses the political situation in China, and provided a sense of general resentment to the Nationalist Party among the Chinese intellectuals and a strong hope for peace among the masses.
  - Notes (Box 2)
  - Transcripts of Interviews, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs and Negatives, 6 folders (Box 2)
- Trip to China 1973, 5 folders
  The second trip to China series contains Rosinger's travel notes, descriptions of images probably to accompany a slide presentation, six rolls of films, and more than 200 black and white photographs. Of interest is Rosinger's interview with Marshall Ye Jianying. The interview was scheduled to be 45 minutes long, but it actually turned out to be an hour and a half. In this lengthy interview, Ye touched upon many important issues on Sino-U.S. relations as well as world politics. Rosinger was one of the few Americans who were granted a visa to enter China at that time, and certainly one of the handful of American scholars who had the opportunity to meet with a high-ranking Chinese leader like Ye Jianying.
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Travel Notes (Box 2)
  - Description of images to accompany slide presentation (Box 2)
  - Photographs and Negatives, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous 1948-1976, 1 folders
  The Miscellaneous series contains scattered materials on Far Eastern studies and a photograph of Lawrence Rosinger with Nehru taken in the early 1950s.
  - 1948-1976 (Box 2)